Guide to the Silas Weir Mitchell papers, 1809-1915 and undated RL.00901
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Silas Weir Mitchell papers
1809-1915 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mitchell, S. Weir (Silas Weir), 1829-1914
RL.00901
1.2 Linear Feet 2 boxes; 1 oversize folder
U.S. physician, neurologist, and author. Papers date from 1809-1915 and include correspondence and documents sent to Mitchell relating to matters personal and professional. Transcripts are often present. Principal correspondents include his relative Mitchell Henry, his publisher Frank H. Scott, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jeffries Wyman, Charles-Edouard Brown-Séquard, Louis Agassiz, Elizabeth Cabot Cary Agassiz, Anna Eliot Ticknor, Sir W. T. Gairdner, Louis Lee Lawrence, Charles Leonard Moore, Julian Stafford Corbett, Harrison S. Morris, T. Lauder Brunton, Sir William Osler, and Hideyo Noguchi, among others. A complete list of correspondents is available in the collection. Papers are arranged chronologically. The principal language is English, although there are some letters in French and German. Also includes a set of Mitchell's diplomas. The papers form part of the Trent Manuscripts Collection and were acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
747 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Silas Weir Mitchell papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2011.
Biographical Note
Silas Weir Mitchell is considered a pioneer in the field of neurology. Born in Philadelphia into a family of physicians, he earned his medical degree in 1850 at the Jefferson Medical College, University of Pennsylvania. His interest in neurology grew out of his experience treating nervous disorders in soldiers during the Civil War. He is well-known for his use of the "rest cure" for hysteria and neurasthenia, particularly in women. He was Charlotte Perkins Gilman's physician, who then indicted this treatment in The Yellow Wallpaper; the treatment was also used on Virginia Woolf, who also condemned the practice. He also promoted the use of electrotherapy and massage. Mitchell was elected president of the Association of American Physicians in 1887 and served as a founder and president of the American Neurological Association in 1908-1909. Mitchell was also a patron of the arts and produced many literary works, including poetry, historical novels, and short stories. He died in 1914 after contracting influenza.
Collection Overview
The papers of physician and neurologist Silas Weir Mitchell date from 1809-1915 and comprise over 700 documents and correspondence sent to Dr. Mitchell relating to matters both personal and professional. Transcripts are often included. Principal correspondents include his relative Mitchell Henry, his publisher Frank H. Scott, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jeffries Wyman, Charles-Éduoard Brown-Séquard, Louis Agassiz, Elizabeth Cabot Cary Agassiz, Anna Eliot Ticknor, Sir W. T. Gairdner, Louis Lee Lawrence, Charles Leonard Moore, Julian Stafford Corbett, Harrison S. Morris, T. Lauder Brunton, Sir William Osler, and Hideyo Noguchi, among others. A complete list of correspondents is available in the first box of the collection. A set of Mitchell's diplomas is also included.
The Silas Weir Mitchell papers form part of the Trent Manuscripts Collection and were acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Medicine -- History; Medicine -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Neurology -- History; Physicians -- Correspondence; Physicians -- Pennsylvania; Philadelphia (Pa.); Brown-S quard, Charles-Edouard, 1817-1894; Brunton, T. Lauder (Thomas Lauder), 1844-1916; Corbett, Julian Stafford,Sir, 1854-1922; Gairdner, W. T., Sir (William Tennant), 1824-1907; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Mitchell, S. Weir (Silas Weir), 1829-1914; Morris, Harrison S.(Harrison Smith), 1856-1948; Moore, Charles Leonard, b. 1854; Osler, William, Sir, 1849-1919; Noguchi, Hideyo, 1876-1928; Wyman, Jeffries, 1814-1874; Ticknor, Anna Eliot, 1823-1896; Agassiz, Elizabeth Cabot Cary, 1822-1907; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
- Silas Weir Mitchell papers, 1809-1915 and undated, 2 boxes, oversize folder
  Collection Overview
  A complete list of correspondents by folder is available in Box 1. Papers are arranged chronologically, with the great majority being correspondence sent to Dr. Silas Weir Mitchell. Transcripts are often present. Undated materials are in a folder at the end of the sequence.
  - 1854-1862, 20 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1863-1865, 18 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1866-1868, 18 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1869-1877, 18 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1878-1879, 8 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1880-1883, 26 items (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1884-1885, 14 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1886, 22 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1887-1889, 32 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1890, 16 items (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1891, 24 items (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1884-1885, 14 items (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1892, 43 items (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1893, 19 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1894, 15 items (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1895, 26 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1896, 22 items (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1897, 27 items (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1898, 24 items (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1899-1900, 33 items (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1901, 10 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1901, 10 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1902, 25 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1903, 18 items (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1904, 21 items (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1905, 18 items (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1906-1907, 35 items (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1908, 26 items (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1909, 24 items (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1910, 25 items (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1911, 15 items (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1912, 12 items (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1913-1915, 34 items (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Undated materials, 61 items (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Scope and Contents
    Undated correspondence, notes, and fragments.
  - Diplomas, 1809-1912 (Oversize-folder 1)